Guide to the Trent history of medicine manuscripts collection, [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Trent History of Medicine manuscript collection [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980, (780 collections; approximately 6,000 items)
  - Jeffries, John, 1745-1819. Card, undated, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician and meteorologist of Boston. Autograph signature on a small card.
  - Jenner, Henry. Letter, 1818, Apr. 22, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Nephew of Edward Jenner. Letter (ALS). Sends vaccine matter and gives detailed instructions on its use.
  - Jenner, William, Sir, 1815-1898. Papers, 1868-1873 and undated, (3 items) (Box 6)
    English physician and professor of pathological anatomy. Two letters (ALS) and a clipping. Jenner writes his brother Charles, announcing his arrival in Edinburgh, relating family news and describing the Scottish countryside. He writes Lady Emilia Gray, inquiring about the credentials of a Mrs. Gordon of Sydney.
  - Jennison, Timothy Lindall, 1761-1845. Papers, 1803-1832, (2 items) (Box 6)
    Physician of Cambridge, Mass. Letter (ALS) and holograph document, signed. Document is a receipt for a rent payment by William Jenks to Jennison. ALS to Jenks relates to a pamphlet to be given to the Massachusetts Historical Society.
  - Jex-Blake, Sophia, 1849-1912. Letter, [Between 1878 and 1912], (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician, founder and dean of the Edinburgh School of Medicine for Women. Letter (ALS). Response to the editor's inquiries regarding the tuition and course of studies at the Edinburgh School of Medicine for Women.
  - Jobert, Antoine Joseph de Lamballe, 1799-1867. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 6)
    French surgeon. Letter (ALS). Announces the date of his arrival in Paris and promises upon his return to visit his friend's mother, who is ill.
  - Jones, Bence, 1814-1873. Papers, 1854-1869, (2 items) (Box 6)
    English physician, chemist and biographer of Michael Faraday. Letters(ALS). Writes on mineral waters and on a letter by Faraday.
  - Jones, Joseph, 1833-1896. Letter, 1885, July 3, (1 item) (Box 6)
    U.S. physician. Letter (ALS). Writes on personal affairs.
  - Jussieu, Antoine Laurent de, 1748-1836. Document, 1842, Febraury 19, (1 item) (Box 6)
    French physician and botanist. Holograph document, signed. A receipt of payment for lattice work performed during January and February of 1842. Signed by Jussieu, among others.
  - Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857. Letter, 1856, Sept. 23, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Physician and Arctic explorer. Letter (ALS). Informs Childs, Philadelphia publisher, that he leaves his present host, the New York merchant and philanthropist Henry Grinnell, for Europe in a fortnight in a last attempt to recover his health.
  - Keate, Thomas, 1745-1821. Letter, 1794, Sept. 24, (1 item) (Box 6)
    English surgeon. Letter (ALS), written at Windsor Castle, to Matthew Lewis. Writes that, in his opinion, yellow fever is not contagious, but rather "an epidemical fever, arising from some general cause". He draws upon observations of cases in Philadelphia and in the West Indies.
  - Keen, William Williams, b. 1837. Letter, 1864, Jan. 27, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Surgeon of Philadelphia. Letter, 1864, Jan. 27, Philadelphia, to Dr. Brinton. Written on the back of an ALS from R. J. Levis to Keen. Both men write regarding efforts to collect surgical casts and make them available to Brinton and the Army Medical Museum.
  - Keller, Johan Christopher Henrik Rummelhoff, 1830-1884. Papers, 1876-1881, (1 item) (Box 6)
    Danish physician, of Nyeborg, who taught in schools for the deaf and blind. Letter (ALS). Writes to Cabinet Minister Jeus Peter Trap and to a Dr. Peterson.
  - Kelly, Howard Atwood, 1858-1943. Papers, 1888-1943 and undated, (116 items, 3 folders) (Box 6)
    U.S. gynecologist and surgeon. Letters (ALS and TLS), cards and reprints. Correspondence to Kelly from Ernest Watson Cushing; from Benjamin Frantz, on the earliest use of ether and chloroform; from William Halsted, on gynecological surgery; from William W. Keen, on yellow fever; from Fielding H. Garrison, on medical history; from D'Arcy Power; and from H. S. Jennings, on evolution. Sir Alexander Russell Simpson, Evelyn Blantyre Simpson, and James Young Simpson, all relatives of Sir James Young Simpson, relate family news. William H. Welch, friend and colleague, writes on personal and professional matters, including the faculty and staff at the Johns Hopkins Medical School, Osler and the founding of the Medical School, medical ethics, the organization of the military medical services, and World War I.
  - Kerner, Justinus Andreas Christian, 1786-1862. Manuscript, 1835, Mar. 20, (1 item) (Box 7)
    German physician, poet and spiritist. Autograph prescription, signed.
  - Kettilby, K. Letters, 1779-1784, (2 items) (Box 7)
    The two letters seem to have been dictated, taken by Mr. Barth. Correspondents are a Mr. Coombes and a Mr. Burns.
  - Kirschner, Martin, 1879-1942. Letter, 1924, June 4, (2 items) (Box 7)
    German surgeon. Letters (TLS). Inquires after the reputation of a Dr. Wichura.
  - Kissam, Ricardus Sharpe, 1763-1822. Document, 1800, Dec. 23, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Lithotomist of New York. Autograph document, signed. Receipt of payment by Judge Ogilvie to Kissam for medical attendance.
  - Kitchiner, William, 1775?-1827. Papers, 1824-1826 and undated, (5 items) (Box 7)
    English physician, writer on gastronomy and optics. Letters (ALS), relating to various social engagements and household arrangements.
  - Kneeland, Samuel, 1821-1888. Letter, 1887, Mar. 9, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Physician and naturalist of Boston. Letter (ALS). Thanks Metayer de Guichainville for Persian stamps received, proposes several subjects for articles, and mentions the manuscript of his work of volcanoes and earthquakes. A clipping on Parisian reaction to the Eiffel Tower is attached to the letter.
  - Koreff, Johann Ferdinand, 1783-1851. Letter, [Between 1800 and 1851?], (1 item) (Box 7)
    German physician with interest in magnetism. Letter (ALS) in French. Sends information on the artificial anus. Includes transcript.
  - Kühnholtz-Lordat, [Geo.?], 1794-1878. Note, 1876, Mar. 8, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Adoptive son of Henri-Marcel Kunholdtz-Lordat, who was librarian of the medical faculty at Montpelier. Note (ANS) sent to the Count de Rivoire de la Batie, apparently accompanying the mailing of one of his adoptive father's books.
  - Küttner, Herman, 1870-1932. Note, 1924, (1 item) (Box 7)
    German surgeon. Autograph note, unsigned, on calling card. Returns thanks for article received.
  - Kussmaul, Adolf, 1822-1902. Manuscript, 1880, Nov. 14, (1 item) (Box 7)
    German physician. Autograph manuscript, signed. Describes results of a detailed examination of a patient's stomach and kidneys and prescribes a course of treatment.
  - La Rive, Auguste de, 1801-1873. Letter, 1846, May 9, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Physician of Geneva. Letter (ALS) relating to the status of French protestant scholarship students at the Academy of Geneva.
  - Laennec, René Théophile Hyacinthe, 1781-1826. Papers, 1825-1826, (2 items) (Box 7)
    French physician, developed method of auscultation, invented the stethoscope. Holograph manuscript, signed, in which Laennec describes the case of a patient "W." A facsimile of an ALS to Baron Cuvier, in which Laennec presents various reasons why he should receive the prize, instituted by M. de Montyon and awarded by the Academy of Sciences, for the most useful discovery in the field of medicine.
  - Lallement, Amédée. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 7)
    French surgeon. Note (ANS). Reports that he will be unable to visit that evening.
  - Lamarcke,__. Papers, 1838-1842, (8 items) (Box 7)
    Physician at the hospital in Gray, France. Letters (ALS). Lamarcke writes to his political patron, the Duc de Marmier in Paris, on affairs of family and friends, local politics and the hospital.
  - Lambert, Maurice. Document, [1918], (1 item) (Box 7)
    French pharmacy student; second lieutenant, French infantry. Typed document. Physician's record of Lambert's stay at the Centre Neurologique, Place de Rouen, for observation and treatment of nervous disorders.
  - Landner, __. Letter, 1834, Oct. 11, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Letter (ALS). Informs Radcliffe of a delay to the start of his lectures at the Mechanics Institution in Liverpool.
  - Langenbeck, Conrad Johann Martin, 1776-1851. Letter, 1806, May 1, (1 item) (Box 7)
    German surgeon and anatomist. Letter (ALS). Resubmits an order returned for lack of a signature.
  - Larrey, Félix Hippolyte, Baron, 1808-1895. Papers, 1799-1847, (9 items) (Box 7)
    French military surgeon. Correspondence of both Félix Hippolyte Larrey and his father, Dominique Jean Larrey. Includes notes from Jean-Antoine-Claude Chaptal and from Marie Guillaume Alphonse Devergie.
  - Lasègue, Charles, 1816-1883. Note, [Between 1835 and 1883?], (1 item) (Box 7)
    French physician and psychiatrist. Note (ANS). Informs addressee that a Dr. Morel, physician in chief at the Rouen Asylum, wishes to visit their patient, Leon Guibout.
  - Latané, John Holladay, 1869-1932. Letter, 1914, Feb. 12, (1 item) (Box 7)
    U.S. Historian. Letter (ALS). Latané responds to Jacobs' inquiries regarding a 1797 letter by Benjamin Rush on slavery. In his opinion, "the framers of the Constitution seem to have regarded slavery as a dying institution, but the invention of the cotton-gin in 1793 gave it a new lease on life".
  - Latouche, Constant François. Letter, 1774, June 28, (1 item) (Box 7)
    French physician. Letter (ALS). Describes an operation successfully performed on the Archbishop of Paris in 1774.
  - Laudun, __. Letter, 1785, July 4, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Physician and doctor of surgery of Tarascon, France (near Montpelier). There are several de Laudun family members who were physicians. Letter (ALS). Asks a Parisian colleague to look after his son, who travels to Paris to study surgery.
  - Lavater, Johann Caspar, 1741-1801. Letter, 1781, Mar. 16, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Swiss physiognomist. Letter (ALS). Writes of Georg Christoph Lichtenberg, who ridiculed Lavater's science of physiognomy, and refuses to arbitrate a dispute between three other physiognomists, Schmohl, Simon and Schweighäuser.
  - Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, 1743-1794. Letter, 1791, Mar. 20, (1 item) (Box 7)
    French chemist. Letter (ALS). Lavoisier, who for some time controlled the monopoly of tobacco in France, advises Doirée to start trading in tobacco for his own account.
  - Lawrence, Effingham. Document, 1786, Apr. 29, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Autograph document, signed. A deposition presented to a grand jury, in which Lawrence accuses his servant, Peter Tom, of theft of opium and other patent medicines, and a Dr. Heerman of selling the stolen goods.
  - Lawrence, William, Sir, 1783-1867. Papers, 1840-1850, (2 items) (Box 7)
    English surgeon. Letters (ALS), including a letter of sympathy to Mr. L. R. Koecker on the occasion of the death of his father, Leonard Koecker.
  - Lawyer, A. Papers, 1838-1842, (3 items) (Box 7)
    Medical student. Letters (ALS) to his father, congressman and attorney Thomas Lawyer (1785-1868), of Lawyersville, Schoharie Co., New York. Letters generally refer to his medical studies.
  - Lazerme, Jacques, 1676-1756. Manuscript, 1723, July 1, (1 item) (Box 7)
    French physician. Autograph manuscript, signed. Record of a case involving calculi and urology.
  - Leblanc, A. Letter, 1830, Oct. 4, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Letter (ALS) regarding a social engagement.
  - Lederer, L. Letter, 1824, Sept. 20, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Letter (ALS) on business matters.
  - Lee, Henry, 1756-1818. Papers, 1793 and undated, (2 items) (Box 7)
    Governor of Virginia (1791-1794). Two copies of a printed "Act to oblige vessels comming from foreign parts to perform quarantine" of the Virginia General Assembly. One copy bears a note by Lee on the reverse, stating that the law expires in October, but that the new law contains the same principles and regulations.
  - Le Fort, Léon Clément, 1829-1893. Note, [Between 1850 and 1893?], (1 item) (Box 7)
    French surgeon. Note (ANS). Asks addressee to bring his "mémoire" to the evening's gathering.
  - Leib, Michael, 1761-1822. Letter, 1806, Dec. 22, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Physician and politician of Pennsylvania. Letter (ALS). Writes of his part in the effort to impeach Governor Thomas McKean and asks Clay to obtain seeds of curious plants from a Captain Lewis for a visiting friend, Henry Muhlenberg.
  - Le Maguet, __. Letter, 1876, Aug. 6, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Physician of Pontivy (Morbihan). Letter (ALS). Writes of the local elections.
  - Leroy d'Étiolles, Jean Jacques Joseph, 1798-1860. Note, [Between 1820 and 1860?], (1 item) (Box 7)
    French physician and inventor of surgical instruments. Note (ANS). Asks a colleague to assist him the next day.
  - Letheby, Henry, 1816-1876. Papers, 1857-1866 and undated, (3 items) (Box 7)
    English physician and chemist. Letters (ALS) relating to arrangements to lecture in chemistry and a brief biographical sketch.
  - Letter, 1864, July 15th, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Petition addressed "To his Excellency The President of the Confederate States of America" from the citizens of Cripple Creek, Wythe County, Va., strongly requesting the exemption of Dr. C.C. Campbell from war duties as he was the only physician in the area. Bears many signatures of male citizens of the town.
  - Lettsom, John Coakley, 1744-1815. Papers, 1785-1813, (9 items) (Box 7)
    English Quaker physician and philanthropist. Holograph, with signature page missing. Writer's references to Waterhouse and Jenner signal his involvement in the promotion of vaccination. Writer also communicates his surprise at Frank's decision to take up a post at the University of Vilna. ALS from Lettsom to Miss Warren briefly mentions Thomas Joseph Pettigrew. Four ALS to Lettsom from various correspondents, B. Wilmer, L. Maclean, J. Murphy and W. May, relate to the Medical Society of London. A transcription, in an anonymous hand, of abolitionist verse by Lettsom is followed by a description of the setting of the gathering at which the verses were presented. On the verso of this is an autograph note, signed by Benjamin Wilson, 1801.
  - Lewis, Dio, 1823-1886. Papers, 1872-1878, (2 items) (Box 7)
    Boston homeopathist, medical reformer and pioneer in physical education. Letters (ALS). Writes to "my dear Holbrook" of his intention to start a school of physical education and to write a book and to Mr. Woolson, inviting both Woolson and his wife to join him that summer.
  - Lewis, William. Letter, 1822, July 4, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Letter (ALS). Reports that his grandson has been vaccinated by a Dr. Andrews.
  - Liebig, Justus, Freiherr von, 1803-1873. Letter, 1836, May 26, (1 item) (Box 7)
    German chemist. Letter (ALS). Liebig refers to Henry's visit to Giessen and inquires after his visit to Paris. He suggests that Henry might be interested in pursuing Edmund Davy's research on gases.
  - Lippe, C. Note, 1883, Oct. 13, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Surgeon of New York. Note (ANS). Thanks addressee for information received.
  - Lisfranc, Jacques, 1790-1847. Note, [Between 1810 and 1847], (1 item) (Box 7)
    French surgeon. Note (ANS).
  - Lister, Joseph, Baron, 1827-1912. Papers, 1900-1902 and undated, (2 items) (Box 7)
    Quaker physician and surgeon, developed antiseptic prevention of wound infections. Two letters (ALS) and a fragment of an ALS. Lister writes to James Burn Russell, inquiring about the use and success of anti-plague sera against the plague in Glasgow, and to Herbert Edward Durham, on the question whether the mosquito is the carrier of the yellow fever agent, suggesting various experimental ways to discover the bacilli and establish their development within the organism of the mosquito.
  - Loder, Justus Christian von, 1753-1832. Papers, 1806-1813, (2 items) (Box 7)
    Surgeon and anatomist. Letters (ALS). Loder writes of his situation and that of friends and family during the Napoleonic Wars, from Narva in 1806 and from Moscow in 1813. In the first letter, he bemoans the defeat of the German states; mentions the student unrest at the University of Halle and the subsequent closing of the university as yet another setback for the German nation; and sees Russia as the only "nation" which can now hope to defeat Napoleon. Loder, educated in Germany, was born in Riga, Estonia, and thus could be considered a Russian. In the second letter, he expresses fierce Russian nationalist sentiments, for which uncharacteristic effusions he explains that he cannot give reasons in writing. Probably he meant to appease the Russian censors. In this letter he details his efforts to organize and oversee the operation of the field hospital in Kassimoff and describes Moscow before and after the siege.
  - Lodge, Oliver, Sir, 1851-1940. Letter, 1918, Mar. 6, (1 item) (Box 7)
    English physicist. Letter (ALS). Informs Lady Murray that at her request he is sending a book to the Hospital at Glasgow.
  - Loiseau, Charles, 1824-1897. Letter, 1871, Mar. 5, (1 item) (Box 7)
    French sanitarian and psychiatrist. Letter (ALS). Declines appointment as an army doctor. Promises, however, to take care of the sick and wounded of the department if necessary.
  - Lombroso, Cesare, 1835-1909. Letters, 1878-1908 and undated, (28 items) (Box 7)
    Italian criminologist. 16 letters (ALS), 12 autograph postcards, signed.
  - Long, Crawford Williamson, 1815-1878. Papers, 1870-1933, (3 items) (Box 7)
    Physician of Georgia, one of the first to use ether as an anaesthetic. Letters (ALS) from Long to the editor of The southern watchman, on the fictional character created by Long, Billy Muckly; a typescript of a poem by Mary McKinley Cobb, In memoriam, Dr. Crawford W. Long, discoverer of anesthesia; and a photostat of James Venable's account with Long for the first half of 1842. The letter and the typescript are annotated by Long's daughter, Emma M.
  - Louis, Antoine, 1723-1792. Letter, 1791, Oct. 1, (1 item) (Box 7)
    French surgeon; secretary of the Royal Academy of Surgery. Letter (ALS). Report of a meeting of the College of Surgeons. English translation available.
  - Louis, P. C. A. (Pierre Charles Alexandre), 1787-1872. Note, [1800s], (1 item) (Box 7)
    French physician. Note (ANS). Asks the President to recommend a doctor from the French garrison in Rome.
  - Lovell, Joseph, 1788-1836. Papers, 1834-1835, (2 items) (Box 7)
    Surgeon General of the U.S. Army (1818-1836). Letters (ALS) to Thomas Aspinwall and to William Jenkins Worth relating to accounts and expenses to be paid by the Surgeon General's Office.
  - Lubbock, John, Sir, 1834-1913. Letter, 1871, Apr. 13, (1 item) (Box 7)
    English banker, politician and pioneer in the experimental study of animal behavior. Letter (ALS). Asks for Evans' opinion in an unspecified matter and suggests that he come to the meetings of the Anthropological Institute.
  - Lyall, Robert, 1790-1831. Note, 1827, Mar. 20, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Note (ANS). Instructs Mr. Buckman to deliver a copy of Lyall's "Travels" to the bearer of the note.
  - Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875. Papers, 1841-1859, (3 items) (Box 7)
    English geologist. Letters (ALS), including a letter from Hugh Swinton Legaré to Samuel Henry Dickson, introducing Lyell, and a letter relating to paleoanthropology, in which Darwin's work is briefly mentioned.
  - M. l'abbé de L'attaignant. Los Tronchinades, undated, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Manuscript in verse in an anonymous hand. Relates to French physician Théodore Tronchin.
  - Mackenzie, James, Sir, 1853-1925. Note, 1917, Jan. 2, (1 item) (Box 7)
    English physician. Note (ANS). Requests a meeting with Bleadnell. On bottom portion of page, Bleadnell notes that he visited Sir James on January 9.
  - Mackenzie, Morell, Sir, 1837-1892. Papers, 1874-1891, (4 items) (Box 7)
    English laryngologist. Letters (ALS). Sends Mr. Garcia a prescription; informs a prospective patient about consultation fees; writes of the release of his book, The fatal illness of Frederick the Noble; and declines an offer to contribute to the periodical, The Ladies Home Journal.
  - Mackie, John. Letter, [Between 1790 and 1853], (1 item) (Box 7)
    Physician of Rhode Island. Letter (ALS). Writes regarding the settlement of an estate.
  - MacNeven, William James, 1763-1841. Letter, 1809, Mar. 28, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Physician and chemist of New York. Letter (ALS). Sends Mrs. Alston a description of a method for obtaining and purifying nitrous oxide.
  - MacNider, William de Berniere, 1881-1951. Papers, 1939-1940, (5 items) (Box 7)
    North Carolina physician and professor of pharmacology. Leters (ALS, TLS and TL). MacNider writes to Dr. W. P. Kavanagh regarding a terminal case of myocardial infarction. Included is a typescript, unsigned, of a letter to MacNider from Kavanagh.
  - Magendie, François, 1783-1855. Letter, [Between 1800 and 1855], (1 item) (Box 7)
    French experimental physiologist. Letter (ALS). Asks him to kindly give three or four baths free of charge to a servant girl of his wife who does not have the means to pay for them. Adds that next time he will recommend better patients.
  - Magnan, Jacques Joseph Valentin, 1835-1916. Letter, 1904 [or 1906], Nov. 11, (1 item) (Box 7)
    French physician. Letter (ALS). Discusses the history and organization of l'Académie de Médecine.
  - Maine, Jacob. Document, 1797, Feb. 7, (1 item) (Box 7)
    Physician of Killingsworth, Conn. Holograph document, signed. A statement of Dodo Pierson's account with Maine. Maine's signature acknowledges receipt of payment.
  - Malgaigne, Joseph-François, 1806-1865. Papers, 1849, Aug 22 and undated, (2 items) (Box 7)
    French surgeon. Note (ANS), including a request to attend his dying daughter, and a recommendation of a M. Vautrin.
  - Malta, Knights of. Document, [1588?], (1 item) (Box 7)
    Document in French from Maltese branch of Knights Hospitaller. On vellum, faded ink. More modern stamp on document indicates that the document was in the "Archives de l'Ordre Malthe."
  - Marcet, Alexander, 1770-1882. Letters, 1802-1823, (86 items) (Box 7)
    Swiss-born physician and chemist, educated at Edinburgh and served at Guy's Hospital in London. Collection of letters, chiefly to Marcet, the majority of which originate with Dr. John Yelloly (1774-1842), physician. Yelloly discusses the Royal Medical and Chirurgical societies at length, comments on Marcet's chemistry work, and congratulates Marcet on his appointment to the military hospital at Plymouth, and later on his appointment as honorary professor of chemistry at Geneva; he also mentions Marcet's wife's own published work on chemistry. Ten letters are from Sir Charles Blagden, and mention Berthollet, Banks, Thomas Young, and Prevost. There are seven letters from Sir Henry Holland asking about the use of Elaterium in cases of dropsy, and twelve letters from Thomas Young (1773-1829), discussing his professional plans, and a paper by Prevost. Includes a letter written in French whose references to Waterhouse and Jenner signal the writer's involvement in the promotion of vaccination.
  - Marey, Etienne-Jules, 1830-1904. Letter, 1870, Apr. 15, (1 item) (Box 8)
    French experimental physiologist. Letter (ALS). Expresses his thanks for help given one of his students.
  - Marjolin, Jean Nicolas, 1780-1850. Note, 1831, May 12, (1 item) (Box 8)
    French anatomist and pathologist. Note (ANS). Asks Boideau to examine the bearer of the note.
  - Massachusetts General Hospital Board of Trustees. Letter, 1816, May, (1 item) (Box 8)